<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse shewing that Protestants are on the safer side, notwithstanding the uncharitable judgment of their adversaries and that their religion is the surest way to heaven.</title>
            <author>Beaulieu, Luke, 1644 or 5-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27169</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1572</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20774</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12046914</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12046914</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53101</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27169)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53101)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 857:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse shewing that Protestants are on the safer side, notwithstanding the uncharitable judgment of their adversaries and that their religion is the surest way to heaven.</title>
                  <author>Beaulieu, Luke, 1644 or 5-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 7-43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Luke Beaulieu. cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:53101:1"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Septemb.</hi> 19. 1687.</p>
            <p>JO. BATTELY, <hi>R<hi rend="sup">mo</hi> in Pri. ac Domino</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>helmo <hi>Archiepiſcop. Cantuar. à Sacris. domeſticis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53101:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE SHEWING That Proteſtants are on the Safer Side, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the uncharitable Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Adverſaries; AND That THEIR RELIGION is the <hi>Sureſt Way to Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwell,</hi> at the Roſe and Crown in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, MDCLXXXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:53101:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53101:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>COming accidentally into a Family always frequented, and of late much diſturbed by ſome <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks,</hi> who by fulminating Damnation againſt all <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> had terrified ſome Friends, I applied my ſelf to clear their Doubts, and to remove thoſe Fears wherewith the Noiſe and Threats of Hell-fire had affected their Minds; This engaged me into a long Debate with one of the Parties who was very poſitive and earnest in maintaining the utter Impoſſibility of being ſaved out of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And upon that it came to be enquired, Whether it be their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to <hi>Rome,</hi> or their Relation to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that Men are to be ſaved by? Whether our State of Eternity depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Talk, or Confidence, or hard Cenſures of Men, or or upon the Truth of our Religion, and our Sincerity in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsing of it? Whether it be the ever-living God, or any mortal Men that make true Religion? Whether that be not the Beſt which beſt agrees with the Divine Revelation? And, whether our Saviour had referr'd us to <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Papal Authority, for the knowledg of Saving Truth; or plainly taught by Himſelf, and by his Apoſtles, all that is requiſit and ſufficient to Salvation?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:53101:3"/>
            <p>About theſe we differ'd: but yet agreed upon the whole, that the great odds in point of ſafety, which they appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend to be betwixt them and us, muſt be grounded upon the Excellency of their Religion above ours; and muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore appear in their Faith, Worſhip, and Morals, which are the eſſential parts of Religion, and make it right or wrong, according as they are themſelves.</p>
            <p>The Talk I then had about this Subject, and the occaſion of it, put me upon writing the enſuing Diſcourſe. Wherein my chiefeſt Aim hath been to fix my Reader upon that which is poſitive with us, and is maintained on all ſides, that being altogether requiſit, and of it ſelf ſufficient to make a Man a good Chriſtian: And then to conſider thoſe Points in belief and practice, about which we differ, and to ſhew on which ſide lies the Advantage for means of Grace, and certainty of Salvation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:53101:3"/>
            <head>The INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>THE Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would not only have all her Dictates received as Divine and true, but would likewiſe have nothing received as ſuch, but what ſhe delivers; inſomuch that her Writers would perſuade us that we can have no Aſſurance of the Truth of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chriſtianity, becauſe we receive it not from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Chair, and rely not on its Authority for the proving of it. As if a Man could not know, and firmly believe that <hi>Jeſus Christ came into the World to ſave Sinners,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as having heard any thing of a Roman Church and her Infallibility. And as if thoſe great Truths which God hath revealed were not to be embrac'd and aſſented to, becauſe they are his, but depended upon the good Pleaſure of a Party of Men, who can no more add greater Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to what God hath declared, than they can make their own Sayings of an equal Authority with God's.</p>
            <p>We can admit that Church for a joint Witneſs with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſtian Churches, that the Bible is the Word of God, and that the Chriſtian Creed is the Catholick Faith: But there is no reaſon to think, that any thing is the more true, or the more neceſſary, meerly becauſe ſhe ſaith it. That which is equally atteſted by all Chriſtian Churches, who were all Depoſitories of the Divine Oracles, and of the Chriſtian Religion, hath a cogent and a clear Evidence: But that wherein ſhe ſtands divided from all the reſt, and bears witneſs only to her own Prerogatives, is either true, becauſe ſhe aſſerts it (which none will dare to ſay) or ought
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53101:4"/>to be proved by the Teſtimony of the whole Chriſtian Church, and of Divine Revelation, which ſhe can never do.</p>
            <p>So we have this great Advantage in thoſe things which we aſſert as Points of Saving Faith, that we have the plain and expreſs Words of Holy Scripture, and the Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the whole Church: whereas thoſe things which we reject, are made a Creed only by one particular Church, not above one hundred Years agone, and have no Ground in Holy Writ.</p>
            <p>Some may diſpute with us about our Rites or Diſcipline, or ſome abſtruſe and diſputable Points: But for that Faith whereon we ground our Hopes of Salvation, nothing can be objected againſt it. It is the ſame wherein every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is baptiſed, the ſame which was before the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and before the Want of it; in Times of greateſt Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity the ſame Faith was profeſt, and in the worſt of Times, under the greateſt Corruptions it was ſtill preſerved: and that not in one Kingdom, or only here in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> but in all Patriarchates, and in all Chriſtian Churches in the World. We have neither added nor diminiſh'd, nor made any Alteration in that Rule of Faith, which is the Badge and the Ground of Chriſtianity. So that as to this Point, our Religion is now as it was long before <hi>Luther:</hi> We have no other Creed than that which was univerſally profeſt all along. Our Diſpute with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is about their new one, made ſince <hi>Luther,</hi> and profeſt no where elſe but in her Communion; that we cannot embrace. It hath neither the ſame Authority from God nor from Men, as hath the Catholick Belief.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:53101:4"/>
            <p>To make this plain here, I ſet the two Creeds at large, to be conſulted as the Reader finds occaſion.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="creeds">
               <body>
                  <div type="creed">
                     <head>The <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Creed,</hi> explained by the <hi>Nicene</hi> and the <hi>Athanaſian,</hi> in what concerns our Saviour's Divinity, but never enlarged until the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>I <hi>Believe in God the Father Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, Maker of Heaven and Earth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And in Jeſus Chriſt, his only Son, our Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Who was concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Holy Ghoſt, born of the Virgin</hi> Mary.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Suffered und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r</hi> Pontius Pilate, <hi>was crucified, dead, and buried.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:53101:5"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>He deſcended into Hell: the third Day he aroſe again from the Dead.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>He aſcended into Heaven, and ſitteth on the Right Hand of God the Father Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>From thence he ſhall come to judg the Duick and the Dead.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I believe in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Communion of Saints,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Forgiveneſs of Sins,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:53101:5"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Reſurrection of the Body,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And the Life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="creed">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:53101:4"/>
                     <head>The Roman Creed.</head>
                     <p>I <hi>Most ſtedfaſtly admit and embrace the Apoſtolical and Eccleſiaſtical Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with the rest of the Conſtitutions and Obſervations of the Roman Church.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I alſo receive the Holy Scripture ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that ſenſe which the Holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church (whoſe it is to interpret it) hath held and doth hold; nor will ever un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand or interpret it otherwiſe than acccording to the unanimous Conſent of the Fathers.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I profeſs alſo that there are ſeven true and proper Sacraments of the new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant inſtituted by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and neceſſary to the Salvation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind (tho not all of them neceſſary to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man) viz.</hi> Baptiſm, Confirmation, the Euchariſt, Pennance, extreme Unction, Orders <hi>and</hi> Matrimony, <hi>all which do confer Grace; and whereof</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, Confirmation <hi>and</hi> Orders <hi>cannot be repeated without Sacriledg.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I likewiſe receive and admit all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and approved Rites of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church in the ſolemn Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the aforeſaid Sacraments.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:53101:5"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>All and every thing which was defined and declared about Original Sin and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification by the most holy Council of</hi> Trent, <hi>I embrace and receive.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I profeſs likewiſe that in the Maſs is offered to God a true, proper and propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatory Sacrifice for the Quick &amp; Dead; and that in the moſt holy Sacrament of the Euchariſt, there is really and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially the Body and Blood, together with the Soul &amp; Divinity of our Lord Jeſus Christ: And that there is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion made of the whole Subſtance of Bread into his Body, and of the whole Subſtance of Wine into his Blood, which Converſion the Catholick Church calls</hi> Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I alſo confeſs that under either Kind or Species only, whole and entire Christ and the true Sacrament is received.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I conſtantly hold that there is a Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory; and that the Souls there detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned are helped by the Suffrages of the Faithful.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>As alſo that the Saints, who reign to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Christ, are to be worſhipped, and prayed to, and their Reliques to be venerated.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I most firmly aſſert that the Images of Christ, of the Bleſſed Virgin, and of the other Saints, are to be had and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and that due Honour and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is to be imparted to them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:53101:5"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I alſo affirm that the Power of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences was left by Christ to his Church, and that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of them is most ſalutary to Chriſtian People.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I acknowledge the Holy Catholick and Apoſtolick</hi> Roman <hi>Church to be the Mother and Miſtreſs of all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: And I promiſe and ſwear true O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Pope of</hi> Rome, <hi>who is Chriſt's Vicar, and Succeſſor to St.</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>the Prince of the Apoſtles.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I alſo without doubt receive and profeſs all other things deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, defined and declared by the ſacred Canons and Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menical Councils, eſpecially by the most holy Synod of</hi> Trent; <hi>and all things contrary to them, with all Hereſies whatſoever, condemned, rejected and curſed by the Church, I likewiſe reject, and condemn and curſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This true Catholick Faith, without which no Man can be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, which at preſent I freely hold and profeſs, I will (by God's help) conſtantly retain and confeſs intire and inviolable to my last Breath, and take care to the utmost of my Power, that the ſame ſhall be taught, held and profest by all under me, and whoſe Care ſhall belong to me in my Office. I the aforeſaid</hi> N. <hi>promiſe, vow and ſwear it: So help me God, and theſe holy Evangils.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Roman Creed it is about which we differ: for as to the Chriſtian Creed there is no Diſpute betwixt us; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that we account it ſufficient, and will profeſs none elſe.</p>
            <p>This is the State of the Difference betwixt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and ours. We ſtand for that Faith which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt of all ſides to be truly Catholick and Apoſtolick; and diſown that <hi>Roman</hi> which they would impoſe upon us.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:53101:6"/>
            <p>I know that they ſeek to retort this Objection of making of new Creeds, and would make the diſtinct Denial of the ſeveral Points of theirs to be in like manner ſo many Articles of ours; as if it were with us as fundamental a Truth, that there is no <hi>Roman Purgatory,</hi> as that <hi>the Blood of Jeſus Christ cleanſeth us from all Sins:</hi> Whereas it is moſt appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent that the Negative of falſe Opinions doth in no wiſe become a Part of the Chriſtian Doctrine, nor of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Creed.</p>
            <p>True Religion is not to ſwell in Proportion to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Errors, for then every new Addition to Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity would make a new neceſſary Article for the rejecting of it, and it would be in the Power of every Hereſiarch to enlarge the Rule of Faith againſt him. Whereas the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith was once delivered to the Saints, and muſt ever remain the ſame, whatever Hereſies ſome Men are pleaſed to broach. That Saints and Images are to be worſhipped, is a Point of the Roman Faith; that they are not, is not a Point of mine; 'tis only a Declaration of my diſowning this Roman Doctrine, as being neither in the Chriſtian Creed, nor in the Word of God. The refuſing of Mens Errors, whether they be Pagans, or any Hereticks, is not a Part of our Belief, but rather of our Disbelief. Our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying that <hi>Jupiter,</hi> or Great <hi>Diana,</hi> or any Creature, though never ſo ſolemnly canoniz'd, are to receive Religious Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, is only a renouncing of Mens Devices, but doth not conſtitute ſo many new Doctrines; only what God hath commanded in this caſe, is Part of our Religion, <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Creed and Religion therefore is ſtill univerſal, and truly Primitive, although our rejecting ſome Points which they have made Part of theirs in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> can be neither ſo Primitive nor ſo Univerſal. What our Church owns for her Saving Belief, is own'd, and ever was, by all
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53101:6"/>Chriſtian Churches; what ſhe rejects from being ſuch, is of a later Date, and was never ſo general. So that inſtead of asking us, Where was our Religion before our Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were forc'd to leave the <hi>Roman</hi> Church? it ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be enquired, why they threw off thoſe ſeveral Tenets contained in the Roman Creed? and then the Queſtion would be plain and fairly ſtated, and might from every Man that hath but read the Bible, receive a clear Anſwer. But it is very unreaſonable to demand ſuch Authorities for refuſing of any new and abſurd humane Inventions, as for the receiving thoſe Truths which God hath expreſly revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and his Church received all along.</p>
            <p>As for the Vices or Vertues of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, or any others, who were engaged to ſtruggle with the Papal Power and Uſurpations, they ſignify nothing to us. The enormous Faults of ſuch as are reputed Supreme and Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Guides of a Party may well reproach them: But our Religion hath no dependence on Hiſtorical Paſſages of any Mens Doings. God's Veracity and Revelation is the Ground we depend upon; Him we worſhip, and in Him we believe, as is to be ſeen in our Publick Liturgies: For that we claim the Warrant of his Word, and the Suffrage of all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Churches, than which no better Ground, nor no higher Authority is ever to be had. If the Roman Creed had the ſame, we would embrace it heartily, for the well-being of our Souls; or if it were leſs repugnant to the Chriſtian In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, we might be perſuaded to comply, or to be ſilent, for the Peace and Tranquillity of our preſent Welfare.</p>
            <p>But my Deſign is only to ſettle and to pacify them that are ſtagger'd and diſturb'd with the ruder Noiſe of Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion daſhing againſt them; and therefore I will purſue
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53101:7"/>things no further than to ſhew, That neither the Judgment of our Adverſaries, nor any thing wherein both Churches diſagree, any ways endangers our future Happineſs: But that as to the ſecuring the eternal Welfare of our immortal Souls, ours is to be preferred before the Roman Communion.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:53101:7"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE ſhewing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Concerns of Eternity being ſo tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendous, and many not ſo well inſtructed as they ſhould, 'tis no wonder if ſome Men are frighted with the fearful Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence pronounced againſt them by the Zealots of the Roman Party. To any Man ſerious or timorous, Threats of Damnation are terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, even in the Mouth of a Mortal Creature: Though it only betrays the Preſumption of any ſinful Man that dares ſit on the Tribunal of his Almighty Judg; yet becauſe ſome are ſo tender and ſo weak in this Point, as to be much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered and diſmayed to ſee themſelves adjudged to Hell, though it were but a Dream or a melancholy Fancy; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it may be worth the while, briefly to ſtate the Caſe, and conſider on what Grounds they proceed that ſo freely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce our Doom. And I doubt not but to make it appear that we want only their good Word, or alſo their good Will, when for Safety and a ſure Foundation we are at leaſt as well as they. It may ſurprize and ſtartle to ſee one ſtare, and with great Confidence denounce that you are a dead Man that cannot live an Hour; but having recovered your ſelf, and reflected upon't, you paſs by without further Harm, and ſmile at the Humour. <hi>There is one Law-giver, who is able to ſave and to deſtroy. Who art thou that judgeſt another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our intire dependence is upon God, as well for the ſtate of Eternity as for the preſent. We do not fall, when we
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53101:8"/>go hence, under a new or an unknown Power, neither are left to Mens Mercy: but the ſame God by whom we were taken out of our Mother's Womb, and to whom we were left, when we hang'd yet upon her Breaſts; he that took care of us, and provided for us here upon Earth, is ſtill to diſpoſe of us in our future State: And we ſhall be judged by him, by whom we were made and redeemed.</p>
            <p>This God whom we now ſerve, and under whoſe Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Dominion we muſt ever remain, is infinitely good, <hi>He would have all Men to be ſaved, and to come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the Truth.</hi> Therefore he doth not ſeek Advantages againſt them, nor lay Snares in their Way, nor wrap up his Saving Light in Obſcurity, but deals with them in much Mercy, making that Grace of his which bringeth Salvation appear unto all Men, that they may know the Way to Life, and clearly ſee what they muſt do to obtain Eternal Happineſs. This, God ſhews Men by that Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation he hath made of his bleſſed Will, how they ought to walk and to pleaſe him: Therein all things neceſſary are very plainly expreſt, that they may be underſtood of all. And for a further Help and a greater Security to Men of all Capacities, a Summary of Divine Truths, ſuch as are fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental and needful, was by times made and propagated, together with the Chriſtian Religion, over all the World. So that we have the Word of God, and the Apoſtolick Creed, both of them always atteſted by the whole Chriſtian Church, as two firm Pillars, whereon to repoſe our ſelves. That we might be ſtrong and immoveable in the Faith, aſſured that we are not impoſed upon by our Guides, and that length of Time hath made no Alteration, but that we hold now the ſame things which were taught by Chriſt, and received of his Church; and that we make nothing neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which from the Beginning was not ſo.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53101:8"/>
            <p>Firſt, then, The Word of God contained in the Holy Bible is, by Conſent of all, that Saving Truth of God by which we muſt live, and by which we ſhall be judged; ſo that whatſoever is there written, is to be embraced as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and as coming from God. Whether it relates to the Creation and the Government of the World, or to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Wonders which God wrought in former Ages, to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his People, and to confirm and atteſt his Revelation; or to the Fall of Man and the Promiſe of a Saviour; or to his Miſſion into the World, and his accompliſhing the great Work of our Redemption; or to the Goſpel-Promiſes, and Doctrines and Myſteries; or to Laws and Rules of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and Inſtitutions of Divine Worſhip; whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it relates to, it is to be embraced with an humble and obedient Faith. Nothing is to be queſtioned that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Bible; all humane Authorities and humane Reaſonings muſt ſubmit to it, for the Bible is the Word of God.</p>
            <p>Go into all the World, and you ſhall find all Churches every where aſſert the ſame as well as we. The <hi>Jews</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur with us in the Divine Authority of the ancient Oracles, before our bleſſed Lord's Coming: But all Chriſtians in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Part, and in every Age of the Church, embrace and reverence both the Old and New Teſtament, as the Book of God, wherein are contained the Declarations of his Will, and the Words of eternal Life. If you enquire what they thought of it, in the firſt or ſecond Ages after our Saviour, or at any other time; or if you go to the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> or <hi>African</hi> Churches, or any the moſt remote Place where Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is profeſt, you ſhall find all agreed in this, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble contains the Doctrine of eternal Salvation, and is the Word of God. This is not a thing wherein the Greeks differ from the Latins, or Proteſtants from the Papiſts; but is the firm Belief of all. This is a moſt conſtant and inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53101:9"/>Tradition, which for Extent of Time and Place is univerſal, and therefore of the greateſt Credit, altogether unqueſtionable.</p>
            <p>So here is a very great Number of Divine and undoubted Truths agreed upon by all the Chriſtian World; even all the plain and clear Propoſitions contained in Holy Scripture. Although they be of things not ſeen, that are paſt or to come; yet being there revealed, they are aſſented to by all. And he that ſhould deny any of them, would be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Chriſtians of all Communions; his refuſing to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg the Truth of any Contents of the Bible, would be interpreted a Denial of God's Veracity, becauſe they are all perſwaded, that the Bible is the Word of God, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Guidance and the Inſpiration of his Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
            <p>He that rejects this Foundation on which all Chriſtians are grounded, ought never to concern himſelf in the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences among them, nor pretend to be of any Church; for by his denying the Truth of that Revelation which they all own to be Divine, and whereon they rely, he makes himſelf an Infidel, and a Party againſt them all. And yet if we could ſee to the bottom of Things, I doubt not but it would appear, that the Diſputes and Contentions which are among Chriſtians, are moſt eagerly promoted by ſuch as deride thoſe great Truths which they all own to be fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental. They that jointly believe the Truth and the Divine Authority of the Holy Scripture, are ſet to wran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling among themſelves about ſome of its moſt obſcure and unneceſſary Places, by them that believe none of it; and for not mutually embracing and practiſing upon thoſe moſt important Points whereon we are agreed, we expoſe thoſe Doctrines of our common Salvation, which we all profeſs, to the Contempt of the prophane and incredulous World.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:53101:9"/>
            <p>Secondly, The other Pillar which together with the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, ſtrongly Supports of our Faith, is the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Creed. We find alſo for this the ſame Conſent of all Chriſtian Churches, they are unanimous in the Belief and Profeſſion of it, and hold all its Articles to be thoſe great and neceſſary Truths without which none can be ſaved. Whereas the ſeveral Contents of the Bible, although equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true, yet are not of an equal Concern, and are too nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous to be carried in mind: There was a Collection of thoſe principal Points which are neceſſary to all, drawn and appointed from the Beginning, as <hi>a Form of ſound Words,</hi> or a Summary of the Chriſtian Saving Faith. This we call the Apoſtles Creed, and this, I ſay, in all Ages of the Church, and in the full Extent of it, hath been received as a Confeſſion of that Faith, without which none can be ſaved. Go to <hi>Rome,</hi> or to <hi>Geneva,</hi> or among the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> or the <hi>Moſcovites,</hi> or the <hi>Greeks,</hi> or <hi>Ethiopians,</hi> as many as call on the Saving Name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> do thus make Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Faith in him. Beſides that each Article is very expreſly and in many Places revealed in the Holy Bible, here is the unanimous Agreement of the whole Church from firſt to laſt, in every Nation, and every Period of Time from the Days of Chriſt, that this is the Badge and Cognizance of a Chriſtian Believer, and that the Profeſſion of this Belief is the Faith once delivered to the Saints, which ſhall endure to the End of the World. Into this Faith, and none other, all Chriſtians are baptized, in all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions, thereby to be made Members of Chriſt's Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, and Heirs of everlaſting Life, if they keep it unto the End whole and undefiled.</p>
            <p>Thus for the believing any of thoſe Points contained in the Apoſtles Creed, or any of the Hiſtories, Promiſes or Commands deliver'd in Holy Scripture, a Chriſtian hath the beſt Warrant he can have for the Belief of any thing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53101:10"/>upon Earth, even the joint Atteſtation of the whole Church of every Age, who teſtified publickly, and ſometimes ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their Teſtimony with their Blood, that the Bible is the Word of God, and the Creed is the Faith of Chriſt. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Chriſtians have fal'n out about other things, as to theſe they are at one. The Belief of this engageth you into no Diſpute with any. Here is a very great Number of moſt marvellous Tranſactions, and gracious Promiſes, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Laws, and important Predictions which are own'd by all to be Divine and infallibly true. Your Belief and Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe depend not upon your Fancy, or the Opinions of private Guides, or the Tradition of your Countrey, or of your Party, but upon the unanimous Witneſs of millions of wiſe and good Men, Apoſtles, Martyrs, Confeſſors, and all thoſe numerous Chriſtian Societies diſpers'd over the World, which make up the univerſal Church.</p>
            <p>Here is enough owned of all ſides to make up an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Agreement betwixt all Churches; The having the ſame Bible, and the ſame Creed, is a very firm and large and laſting Foundation for Peace. Here are all things that are of the greateſt Moment for Faith and a good Life, for the Service of God and the Salvation of our Souls, every where receiv'd and profeſt. He that ſhould weigh the Importance of each of thoſe Truths which are acknowledged by all, would wonder what it is that can divide Chriſtians, and make them ſo fierce and uncharitable one againſt another. We ſee Bigots of different Communions damn and deſtroy one another, as if they were not Partakers of the ſame Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and joyned together by owning the ſame God and the ſame Saviour, and all the chiefeſt Articles of the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Beſides Mens Ignorance and Malice and intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Zeal, no account can be given of the unbeſeeming Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of Chriſtians among themſelves; but that the things wherein they differ are of a preſent Concernment,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53101:10"/>for Wealth or Dominion. Secular Intereſt and humane Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions no doubt have made the Breach, and they that ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laugh at all Religion, and neither regard the Creed nor the Word of God, ſet on the Zealots to diſpute, and for their own Ends make uſe of the Contention; when all this while there is a vaſt Collection of Truths for Comfort and Contempt of the World, for Meekneſs and mutual Love, profeſt to be firmly believ'd by all Parties engag'd.</p>
            <p>But as Men are always craving and purſuing new things, rather than they will make an Eſtimat of what they have receiv'd, becauſe they love to extend their Deſires, rather than to be ſatified, and to be thankful; ſo they rather chuſe to wrangle and diſpute about the meaneſt Punctilios where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are at odds, than to reſt in the greater things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are agreed, becauſe they love to talk and to contend, better than to practiſe and embrace each other.</p>
            <p>This unſettles ſome Men that they know not what to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and gives great occaſion to the prophane to deſpiſe Religion, as if all the Talk about it were arbitrary and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain; they magnifie the Variety of Opinions, and make as if the whole were matter of Conteſt, when they ſee the Contenders act as if they were agreed about nothing. Whereas I ſay, all the great Articles have always been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtioned, notwithſtanding the Peeviſhneſs of ſome, and the ill Deſigns of others, ſtill the ſame Rules of Holineſs, and the ſame Points of Belief, have remained conſtant and embraced by all: The ſame Divine Revelation and the ſame Chriſtian Faith have every where prevail'd, and in the midſt of all Diſputes been preſerved and acknowledged. So that the whole Subſtance, and all the neceſſary Parts of Religion, have always been ſacred, confeſt and reverenc'd by all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches.</p>
            <p>The twelve Articles of our Creed, and all the uncontro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted. Truths revealed in Holy Scripture, make up a Body
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53101:11"/>of Divinity, ſo full, ſo excellent, and ſo comprehenſive, that if we compare it with the Uncertainties and Diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that were every where in the Heathen World, at the firſt preaching of Chriſtianity, we ſhall look on its Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors as very harmonious and very well agreed. There were never ſo many things ſo Great, ſo Wonderful, of ſo infinite a Concern to Mankind, ſo ſtrongly atteſted, or ſo firmly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved by ſuch infinite Multitudes of civiliz'd and knowing Men in all Parts of the World, for ſo many Ages together.</p>
            <p>Here is a Foundation whereon every good Chriſtian may build Peace and Charity towards all his Brethren, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Countries or Communions they be, and may eſtabliſh a ſure Hope of eternal Happineſs to his own Soul: if he doth heartily profeſs and obey thoſe undoubted Truths which are embrac'd and acknowledged by all Chriſtian Churches. He that is fully perſuaded of the Truth of Chriſtianity, and willing to depend for his Salvation upon that plain and eſſential Part of it, which is confeſſed by all, and to lay the great Streſs of his Hopes and of his Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon his Creed, rather than upon controverted Points; he hath what will comfort his Soul, and encourage him to live well; and he is ſafe, peaceable and unmoveable in the midſt of all Diviſions: he may be doom'd, and called Names by them that would impoſe their Opinions as Articles of Faith; but it doth him no harm, whilſt he ſtands firm upon the Rock of the Chriſtian Creed, and the Chriſtian Life together.</p>
            <p>Theſe two are acknowledged of all ſides, to be both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite and ſufficient to Salvation: Faith and Works toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther making up the whole Condition of that Goſpel-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to which is annexed the Promiſe of eternal Life. Therefore in enquiring why they are all condemn'd as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates, that are not of the Roman Communion, we muſt conſider what are the Advantages peculiar to that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:53101:11"/>
            <p n="1">I. Whether their Faith be more ancient and Catholick.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Whether their Worſhip be purer, more conformable to God's Word.</p>
            <p n="3">III. And whether their Righteouſneſs exceeds that of all others.</p>
            <p n="1">I. I begin with that Faith which is peculiar to <hi>Rome,</hi> and is at large ſet down in the Introduction. It indeed contains more Articles than that of any other Church, and it may ſtill receive further Encreaſe, whilſt their Popes and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils can make and impoſe new Definitions as neceſſary; but we believe that Saving Truths are neither made by Mens Authority, nor evidenced by Number. We are contented with that Faith once delivered by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and from the Beginning received by the whole Church, and for this are declared Hereticks, and adjudged to Perdition.</p>
            <p>That Roman Faith about which we differ, is made ſo eſſential and ſo neceſſary, that their Converts are appointed by the Roman Pontifical, in anſwer to the Biſhops Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that reconciles him to make an expreſs Profeſſion of it; and if he were a noted Heretick, even to ſwear to it; condemning all to Damnation that embrace not the ſame; and promiſing that if ever he acts or believes any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that Oath he takes with both his Hands on the holy Evangils, he will ſubmit himſelf to the Severity of the Canons.</p>
            <p>Although we be ſo far agreed with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (as hath been ſeen before) yet they lay ſo great a Streſs upon their new Creed, and derive ſo much of their Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from it, That it is an aſtoniſhing and formidable Change to paſs from our Church into theirs. Beſides the Surpriſe of their publick Worſhip, which by a great Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of Ceremonies, Images, and the Latin Tongue appears
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53101:12"/>very ſtrange: They have a preſcribed Form of reconciling Hereticks, to which none can ſubmit, but they that are ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſuaded that thoſe Opinions, which became a Creed ſince the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> are Part of that Saving Truth of God, which muſt be believed and profeſt under Pain of eternal Damnation.</p>
            <p>It is not, as ſome may fancy or perhaps are told when ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited to change, that they ſhall find it very eaſy, and be received upon what Terms they pleaſe: But the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as all other wiſe Societies, hath its fixt Rules and Forms, and follows them without taking Notice of the Talk or Thoughts of private Perſons. There is nothing can juſtify the Change, or make it tolerable to a Man of Conſcience, but the being convinc'd of the Truth and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of theſe Roman Doctrines, which thitherto were no Part of his Creed. When he hath ſearch'd and us'd all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per means to underſtand the Points in Diſpute, and to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy himſelf, and finds himſelf thoroughly perſuaded that there is no Salvation in our Church, and that the Belief and Worſhip peculiar to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are truly Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and the neceſſary Terms of our Acceptance with God, then is he oblig'd to follow his Light, and to make Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what he believes to be Truth. But till a Man be thus convinc'd, his forſaking ours to joyn with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is a great Prevarication againſt God and Men, that will make him odious to both, and be inexcuſable here and hereafter. The formal Abjuration of all that the Roman Church doth condemn, and the ſolemn Profeſſion with a ſacred Oath of all her Religious Doctrines and Practices in their full Latitude, (as is pretended in the Roman Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical) ſhould make every doubting Perſon amonſt us very ſerious and very inquiſitive, cleerly to know what he doth leave, and what he muſt embrace, if he reſolves to forſake ours, and embrace the Roman Communion.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:53101:12"/>
            <p>The caſe will be much more tolerable with them that were born and educated in that Perſuaſion, if they are in a Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take; they having never profeſs'd, nor perhaps had means to know any thing elſe, is a Plea of which they are not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, who grown to Years of Diſcretion, turn from one Church to another. Theſe had need take great Care that they deal uprightly, and examine to the Bottom of things, otherwiſe they mock God and Men, and muſt expect to fare accordingly.</p>
            <p>I do not deny, but that Perſons of Underſtanding and Sincerity may be prevail'd upon to paſs from ours into the Roman Church, for whilſt Men are mortal they may err and be impos'd upon: And may they all obtain Mercy that truly fear God, and embrace what they judg to be his Truth, (though they be miſtaken) I only ſay, that no Man edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated amongſt us that really believes his Chriſtian Creed, and would not throw his Soul away, can make Profeſſion of the Roman Faith, till he becomes fully convinc'd of its Truth and Neceſſity. For now it is not as it was before the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> when the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf had no other Confeſſion of Faith, but only the Chriſtian which is common to all Churches, and thoſe Opinions which have ſince become Articles of the Roman Faith, needed not be explicitly profeſt, if they were but let alone and not diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt: Whereas now ſince <hi>Pius</hi> the 4th, Hereticks ſo called, that become Proſelytes, muſt make a ſolemn and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Declaration, that they believe every thing that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth either teach or practiſe, and that they will ſubmit and conform intirely to all that ſhe preſcribes either for Faith or for Divine Worſhip. This I ſay no Man of Conſcience or Honour can do, till he become equally perſuaded of the Truth and Neceſſity of the Roman, as of the Chriſtian Creed.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:53101:13"/>
            <p>Confidence proves nothing, and makes nothing to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Divine, and we all know that Religion is not what ſome Men will call ſo: neither can we believe as we would, or as we are bid; we muſt have ſufficient Reaſons that thoſe things are from God, which are propoſed to our Faith; ſo that perſuaded, as we are, we might for Temporal Deſigns play the Hypocrites and diſſemble, but we can never become Proſelytes to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And whilſt we have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to believe that thoſe Articles of Faith, which are peculiar to that Church, are rather contrary to God's Revelation than contained in it, and ſo think it our Duty to diſown their Roman Creed: We are ſo far from apprehending our ſelves to be in danger of Damnation for ſo doing, that we rather believe we ſhould incur that Danger, if againſt our Perſuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Conſcience we ſhould ſolemnly proteſt and declare thoſe things to be our Belief and our Faith, which indeed are not ſo.</p>
            <p>How juſt and material are our Objections againſt each particular Doctrine which <hi>Rome</hi> would impoſe upon us, is to be ſeen in many of the late Treatiſes upon thoſe Subjects: So here I ſhall give no further Account why we reject the Roman Creed, than by making upon it theſe three general Reflections, which alone might be ſufficient to prove that it can in no wiſe be neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Roman Creed ſeems to be calculated for the Meridian of This World, rather than for the obtaining the Happineſs of That which is to come. The Chriſtian Creed doth make no Man greater or richer here on Earth; it is a Profeſſion of our Faith in God, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, which unites us to him, engageth us to love and to ſerve him, and to confeſs Chriſt before Men, and obey his Goſpel; the end of it is to make us hope well and live well, to give us Comfort againſt all Sorrows, and Strength againſt all Temptations. But the Roman Creed makes the Roman
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53101:13"/>Court very great and very rich, and makes Men have a great dependence upon it. It eſtabliſheth thoſe Opinions which much advance the Roman Dominion, making <hi>Rome</hi> to be the Mother and Miſtreſs of all Churches; engaging Men to ſubmit intirely to her, in embracing all her Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Conſtitutions; and obliging all hers that have any Power, to uſe it to the utmoſt, to bring all Men, as they are able, under her Obedience.</p>
            <p>Then for Gain you have ſeveral Articles, the Doctrine of Purgatory, and of Indulgences, the Worſhip of Saints and Images, which doth not exclude Gifts and Oblations to them; and the Sacrifice of the Maſs offered, as they are paid for it, for the living or for the dead; beſides all the Appeals to <hi>Rome</hi> and the Bulls and Expeditions from it: Read their whole Creed over again, and you will clearly ſee that it all makes for the Empire, or the Profit of <hi>Rome.</hi> 'Tis a ſhrewd Suſpicion that they that have made it, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd it upon the World, did therein regard their own Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage more than the Truth of Chriſtian Religion. When the old univerſal Chriſtian Creed makes all for the Honour of God, and for the Sanctification and Salvation of human Souls, and this new particular Creed is all for the Glory and the Power of <hi>Rome;</hi> who that hath not reſign'd up his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but will be forc'd to think, that the one is to bring Men to Heaven, and the other to bring Profit to <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A Man will be ſo much the more confirm'd in this O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, when he ſhall obſerve that the Roman Zeal is all turned this Way. The Endeavours of their Zealots are much greater to make Men of the Roman Perſuaſion, as to the controverted Points, than to make Chriſtians in what we are all agreed: and amongſt them a Man that believes the Bible and the ancient Creeds is as much damn'd and hated as if he were a meer <hi>Turk</hi> or <hi>Heathen.</hi> Their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings againſt them whom they call Hereticks, have been
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53101:14"/>more bloody and violent than againſt meer Unbelievers; as if owning the ſame God and Saviour, and the ſame Articles of Hope and Redemption were nothing, except we alſo own the ſame Submiſſion to <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be reckoned as an Inſtance of their great Earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to progagate their Creed, that their later Miracles, for more than theſe five hundred Years, are all in the behalf of it. The Faith once delivered to the Saints, was eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by thoſe ancient Miracles recorded in the Bible: But this Growing Faith of <hi>Rome</hi> is recommended to Peoples Belief by later Wonders, ſuch as their Legends and Brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries, and many Books of Devotion contain. I need not ſay that many of thoſe Miracles here in the Weſtern Church are ſo dubious and ill-contriv'd, that they make little for the Credit of thoſe Doctrines which they are deſign'd to vouch: I only note that they are all intended for to make credible thoſe Points of the Roman Faith which are deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the Teſtimony of God's Word, and of the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church: and that if we had not better Miracles, and much better atteſted, for the Proof of that Religion that came from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> than they have for that which came from <hi>Rome, Libertines</hi> would not want an advantageous Plea to juſtify their Infidelity.</p>
            <p>And, 3. We may add, that this Roman Creed is both new and confin'd, whereas the Chriſtian is as Catholick as the Church it ſelf; that is, is equally extended to all Times and Places, was ever every where receiv'd, and is now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in all Churches, and in all Parts of the World. Inſtead of this Univerſality for Ages and Extenſion, the Roman Creed bears date, 1564, and being dated from <hi>Rome,</hi> is profeſt by none but thoſe of that Communion, which are but few, in compariſon with the reſt of the Chriſtian World. So that if you paſs into the <hi>African,</hi> or <hi>Greek,</hi> or Eaſtern Churches, which are vaſt and numerous, you ſhall
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53101:14"/>find no other Creed but that of the Apoſtles, explained by the <hi>Nicene</hi> and the <hi>Athanaſian;</hi> if in ſome of theſe Places they have ſome of the Roman Opinions, or ſome of their own as doubtful and new, yet they have no other Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Faith, than as we have in our Reformed Churches in the <hi>West.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay even in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the third Seſſion of the <hi>Tridentine</hi> Council, 1546, they made a Decree, that according to the Example of the Fathers, <q rend="margQuotes">they would make a Confeſſion of that Faith which in ancient times had been an impenetrable Shield againſt all Hereſies, which alone had been uſed for the Converſion of Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, for the Confuſion of Hereticks, and for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the Faithful;</q> and then repeated the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed and no more; declaring, <q rend="margQuotes">That that was the expreſs and formal Faith of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that Faith which is the Principle of Chriſtian Unity, and the ſure and only Foundation againſt which the Gates of Hell ſhall never prevail.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Happy had it been for the Chriſtian World, if this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had ſo remain'd; and the Roman Articles under <hi>Pius</hi> 4. eighteen Years after, had not been made a neceſſary and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Part of the Catholick Faith. However 'tis to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd further, that even now in the Roman Church, when they baptize Children or grown Perſons, they uſe none but the Apoſtles Creed; and to make them Members of Chriſt and of his Church, and Heirs of his Kingdom, oblige them to the Profeſſion of no other Articles, but thoſe that are the ancient Confeſſion of Faith common to all Chriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Nay, more, whilſt they live in that Communion in all Acts of Worſhip, and when they die in it, and are to make the laſt Confeſſion of that Saving Faith, of which they ſoon expect the End and Conſummation, they uſe none but the three Catholick Creeds; the Roman ſerves only to tie
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53101:15"/>all Power and Government to St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute Hereticks withal. So that this Roman Creed being for Temporal Advantages, being not contain'd in the Word of God, nor proved by the Teſtimony nor by the Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Primitive Church, nor received by former Ages, nor by any Church but the Roman, nor by that but very lately, and only in ſome caſes profeſt: we have great reaſon to believe, that it is in no wiſe neceſſary to Salvation. The Chriſtian and univerſal Creed having been eſteemed ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient without any other, for more than fifteen hundred Years, ought to be ſo eſteemed ſtill, without this Addition, which is proved but by very unlikely and uncertain Miracles, and by the Atteſtation of but that one particular, Church for whoſe Wealth and Grandeur it ſo intirely makes.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, we ought no ways to be diſmay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the frightful Words or Countenance of any that pronounce us accurs'd and damn'd, becauſe we hold not, nor can believe what <hi>Pius</hi> the 4th did lately declare to be <hi>de Fide</hi> requiſite to Salvation. We ſhall find ſaving Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Comfort enough in the Chriſtian Creed, which God's Word expreſly confirms, and the whole Church hath ever own'd, if we embrace and ſtudy more and more the Divine and invariable Truths it contains, and ſincerely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to lead our Lives accordingly.</p>
            <p n="2">II. What I have affirmed of the Roman Faith, is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood alſo of the Roman Worſhip: That Part of it which is not approved by us is very bad; palliated or reproved by the cunningeſt or wiſeſt of their Church; or however no ways neceſſary, which is all I am at preſent concerned in.</p>
            <p>Indeed as to the Eſſentials of Divine Worſhip all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are agreed, That God ſhould have our Prayers and Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt our Mediator; even the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53101:15"/>matter of our Requeſts is fixt and uniform amongſt all that own the Lord's Prayer; ſo far the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath many excellent and ancient Compoſures, very unlike thoſe new ones we reject. That part of their publick or private Worſhip which is grounded upon the Chriſtian Creed, is very good: and if they went no further, we might as law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully joyn with them, as they might with us. We have inſerted nothing doubtful or controverted in our Offices of Religion, nothing but what as to the ſenſe is uſed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by all Churches. Had they done ſo, and extended their Worſhip no further than could be juſtified by that Chriſtian Belief which is common to all, the Differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them and other Chriſtians had been much leſs, and more reconcileable. But they have turned all the Points of their new Creed into Exerciſes of publick Religion: and theſe we do not think to be acceptable to God, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to acquit us of that Adoration and Service which we ow to his Divine Majeſty.</p>
            <p>We are perſuaded that without making or worſhipping Images of God, we may pay him that Homage which he requires of us; that if we devoutly commemorate our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Paſſion, and with thankful Hearts put our Truſt in the Merits of it, we ſhall not need to worſhip the Figure of his Croſs; and that if we lift up our Hearts to Heaven, to adore him on the Right Hand of God, we need not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Hoſt here on Earth, which many Chriſtians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to be only the Sacrament of his Death, and none can be ſure to be the Subſtance of his natural Body; no not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Tenents of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe that Part of their Worſhip which relates to Creatures; the ſolemn Bleſſing or conſecrating Images, that being hallowed, they may be fit to be ſet up to receive In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe and Oblations and many Honours, and to excite their Devotion to Saints and Angels: their manifold Pilgrimages
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53101:16"/>and Prayers to thoſe beatified Creatures; The great depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence they expreſs to have upon their Interceſſion, their Merit and their Power; The many Miracles and Mercies they are ſaid to receive from them; And the high Celebrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Returns of religious Gratitude which they render to them: All theſe which make too great a Part of their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and private Devotions, we have great reaſon to believe to be inconſiſtent with God's revealed Will, and with our Duty and Obligations to him; or however, no ways ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</p>
            <p>I appeal to them that have either read the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or learned the Creed, the Lord's Prayer, and the ten Commandments, which all Churches teach to be the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Chriſtian Religion, whether our calling upon him in whom we believe, and ſerving him alone that hath declared himſelf jealous of his Honour, and uſing no Images in our Addreſſes to him that hath forbid them, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching to God by that one Mediator whom he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and who died and merited all for us, and bad us come to him, and uſe his Name alone in all our Requeſts; Whether this Worſhip which is paid to God amongſt us, be not more conformable to his holy Word, and to the Grounds of our common Chriſtianity, than that which is eſtabliſhed in the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> Whatever they may think of us where the Inquiſition reigns, and under it blind Ignorance, and a terrible Averſion againſt them that are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Hereticks; yet elſewhere Men of better Senſe and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Inſtruction, though of the ſame Church, can hardly pronounce us to be God's Enemies, and the Objects of his Wrath, becauſe we are afraid to give his Glory to others, and to tranſgreſs his Laws: or however their Thoughts will not alter the caſe, and can do us no Harm, we having a Rule of God's own preſcribing to believe and to worſhip by, and whilſt we render to God the things that are God's,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53101:16"/>we need not fear the raſh Cenſures of uncharitable Men.</p>
            <p>We have the Warrant of Holy Scripture, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence and Approbation of all Chriſtian Churches for the Worſhip eſtabliſh'd in our Church: if accordingly we ſerve God with Sincerity and Devotion, we ſhall have the Reward of them that diligently ſeek him; however we tranſgreſs no Law of his, and we run no Risk: But if the worſhipping of Saints and Images ſhould prove unaccepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the Papiſts run a great Danger, they having neither Antiquity nor Scripture for the ſame, whilſt the Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their Fellow Chriſtians, and ſome Divine Prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are <hi>point-blank</hi> againſt it.</p>
            <p n="3">III. As for the Neceſſity of a good Life, our Church recommends it at leaſt as much as the Roman. All Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians believe a Judgment to come, and a Retribution to Men according to their Works; ſo we have all the ſame Promiſes of God, and the ſame Rewards propounded to encourage us to do good; we believe the ſame Threats and the ſame Puniſhments to deter us from Evil; we all think our ſelves obliged to Morality, and to be truly vertuous, knowing that without Holineſs no Man ſhall ſee God: and I make no doubt but that in other Chriſtian Communions as well as in ours, there are many who truly fear God and work Righteouſneſs. The Difference betwixt us and the Roman Church, is not whether or no we ought to be good; but every one in either Church, according to his Sincerity and his firm Perſwaſion of the Truth of Chriſtianity, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to approve himſelf to the Searcher of Hearts; ſo far we are agreed. They have many things in their Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Creed, and in their Worſhip, which we cannot approve; but we have the ſame Rules of Life, the ſame Divine Laws to direct our Obedience.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:53101:17"/>
            <p>And I would to God we did all join in thoſe things which admit of no Diſpute, and wherein we are all agreed, and did lay the great Streſs of our Hopes and of our Endeavours on them, <hi>viz.</hi> the hearty Profeſſion of the ſame Chriſtian Creed, the ſincere Worſhip of the ſame God, Father, Son, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, and a ſerious Earneſtneſs to follow the Example and the Precepts of our common Saviour, and to live in this preſent World ſoberly, righteouſly and godly: Theſe that are the great things of God, and the Foundations of Chriſtian Religion, and of true Goodneſs being owned on both ſides, if they were minded as our Intereſt in them, and their Certainty do require, would go near to compoſe our Differences in other things, and to reſtrain that uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Zeal which hath doom'd to Damnation Millions of good Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>However, they that truly believe all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, and worſhip God according to his Will, and our Saviour's Inſtitutions, and are careful to live like Chriſtians worthy of the Goſpel, need not regard thoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, nor fear thoſe Judgments which proceed only from Men; they may be true and happy Saints both here and hereafter, that have for Faith, and the Service of God, and for a Holy Life all that is of Divine Appointment, without the Roman Additions. Our rejecting what the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath for her Intereſt impoſed, where her Power doth reach, will in no wiſe exclude us from Heaven, if we be true to what we own. If by our Life and Profeſſion we confeſs Chriſt here before Men, and are not aſhamed of him, nor of his Words, we need not fear he ſhould hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſown us, becauſe of their Anger that would have us take for Goſpel whatever they dictate. Damnation ſhall not be inflicted according to Mens Paſſions and Uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs; we ought to run from the Danger of it, as far as is poſſible, by preſerving that Faith, we were baptized into,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53101:17"/>pure and undefiled, and by living according to it: But had the Promiſes of Mercy and Salvation been annexed to our Submiſſion to <hi>Rome,</hi> either the unverſal Church would have clearly expreſſed it in making Men Members of Chriſt, and Heirs of his Kingdom, or to be ſure God would have revealed it. And ſeeing none of theſe is done, it doth plainly demonſtrate that ſuch a Submiſſion is deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for Temporal Power, but no ways requiſite to bring Men to Heaven, and that conſequently the hard Sentence of Roman Bigots againſt us, may be prejudicial to them, but can do us no Harm.</p>
            <p>This might ſuffice to ſhew that we are ſafe notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their Outcries of Damnation againſt us, that Part of their Religion which is called <hi>Popery,</hi> being no Part of God's revealed Will and Saving Truth, nor of the Primitive and Catholick Chriſtianity embraced by the whole Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p>In point of Faith, or of Divine Worſhip what is pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to them is far enough from being neceſſary: and for Rules of Converſation we have the ſame Precepts, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the ſame Promiſes and the ſame Puniſhments. So that though we reject many of their own Inventions, yet ſtill we want nothing neceſſary to Salvation, and in order to it, they have no Advantage over us.</p>
            <p>But I may not ſtay here. The Intereſt of Truth and human Souls obligeth me to ſay farther, that we are ſafer in our Church, and have ſeveral Advantages for the obtaining Comfort and eternal Happineſs, of which they are deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſay that we are ſafer. What we believe as an Article of Faith, is undoubtedly true, owned by all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in all Ages of the World, and plainly revealed in God's Word; whereas thoſe Traditions which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath tack'd to the ancient Faith, are newly coyn'd,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53101:18"/>yet more newly made a Creed, are not warranted by Divine Revelation, nor embraced by Chriſtians of other Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. And what a Preſumption is it to change the Terms of Salvation, and make thoſe things neceſſary which God hath not preſcribed, and the Chriſtian Church for many hundred Years hath not owned as a Part of her Saving Faith?</p>
            <p>This is ſo like adding to the Book of God, preaching a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Goſpel, and teaching for Doctrines the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Men; that we think our ſelves much ſafer within the ancient Boundaries, and look upon it as a very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Attempt, to make new Creeds and impoſe them upon Mens Conſciences, eſpecially when thoſe Additions are not only beyond what is written, but alſo of another Nature, and even contrary. The Chriſtian Creed is for Life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, the Roman for the Roman Greatneſs; the Chriſtian expreſſeth our Obligations to God, and our dependence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, the Roman is a Profeſſion of Subjection to <hi>Rome;</hi> the Chriſtian engageth Men to ſerve God only, the Roman to worſhip Creatures alſo; the Chriſtian makes our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Redeemer to be our only Mediator, the Roman joyns to him the bleſſed Saints and the Bleſſed Virgin. There are ſo many things in all Appearance very irreconcileable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe two Confeſſions of Faith, that the Roman can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſafe; and that we may conclude without Uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs, that they of that Perſuaſion that ſhall attain to Heaven, ſhall not come thither by the Help of the Roman Doctrines, but by diſcharging their Baptiſmal Engagements which are the ſame with ours, and by profeſſing the ancient common Creed of all Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>The Points of their own Creed are ſo far from condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to Mens Salvation, that they rather will prove great Hindrances to it. They engage Men in a Worſhip very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to what we read in the Apoſtolical Writings, or the antient Fathers. Beſides the unknown Tongue, and the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53101:18"/>maim'd Communion, there is ſo much of it that is meerly humane and ceremonious, ſo much of it that relates to the Souls in Purgatory or the Saints in Heaven, that we wiſh it may meet with Pardon, but cannot think it ſhould find Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance. There are ſo many ſtrange Exorciſms and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crations in their Rituals and Pontifical, that after having read the Bible, a Man can never think theirs to be that Worſhip in Spirit and in Truth, which the Goſpel appoints. We dare not offer to Almighty God what is ſo like to be injurious to him, and ſo unlike his own Inſtitutions; and have much greater Aſſurance to have our Sacrifice of Prayers and Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes accepted, when according to Divine Appointment we offer it to God, in the Name of his bleſſed Son.</p>
            <p>The ſame holds alſo for vertuous living and Improvement in Goodneſs, that their new Doctrines are rather Obſtacles to, than Helps towards it. The great dependence upon <hi>Rome</hi> and the Papal Power, hath made many of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion very ill Subjects, and many more very cruel and uncharitable to all other Chriſtians. The making a whole State of Sin, although known and perſiſted in, yet to be a State of Pardon and Safety, conſiſtent with the Love of God; the buying and Imputation of other Mens Merits and good Works; the eaſy Purchaſe of many Indulgences, the cuſtomary and frequent Abſolutions for mortal Sins; the Patronage of the greateſt Saints to the greateſt Sinners, when they are their particular Votaries: ſuch prevailing Opinions as theſe abate much of the Neceſſity of a ſerious and ſpeedy Repentance and earneſt Purſuits after Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and too much gratify the Corruptions of Men that are deſirous to enjoy their Luſts, and not loſe the Hopes of Heaven. So if Mixture of falſe and uncertain Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with their Faith; if a Worſhip very corrupt, and very ſuperſtitious; and if Doctrines apt to betray Men to a careleſs and vicious Life: if theſe can endanger humane
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53101:19"/>Souls, we cannot think them ſafe in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> So far as they differ from us, in their Additions to the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Faith, ſo far they are in danger. We pronounce no Sentence, and we pray Divine Mercy to pardon them that err in the Simplicity of their Heart: But their Errors and ſuitable Practices may be the Ruine of many, and our Charity can ſave none. Bleſſed be God, we are ſafer, and have many Advantages for Comfort and for Holineſs, of which they are deſtitute.</p>
            <p>Men of a timorous and a tender Conſcience amongſt them, can never have a comfortable Knowledg and Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their having confeſt all their Mortal Sins, or all thoſe Circumſtances that alter the kind: nor of the Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Prieſt, which is neceſſary to make effectual his Abſolutions; nor of the Validity of any Sacerdotal Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations and Conſecrations, all which depend upon ſceret Intentions or Irregularities, which may be incurr'd many ways, and may proceed ſo far as to be irremediable; of theſe which according to their Principles, ſo much concerns their Happineſs, a thoughtful Man (I ſay) can never be ſo ſure as to make him rejoyce in Hope, and have a ſolid Peace. And what a ſad Proſpect is it to them that think the Sufferings of this preſent Life ſo very grievous, that after all their Pains and Charges to gain Pardons and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, and Prayers for their Souls, they can have no Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance without a Miracle, but that they ſhall lie hundred of Years in ſcorching Flames, paying the Score of thoſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Puniſhments which were due to their Sins.</p>
            <p>Beſides the Uncomfortableneſs of theſe Roman Tenents, they want in that Communion the Benefit of thoſe Divine Inſtructions which were written for our Learning; <hi>that we through Comfort of the Scriptures might have Hope.</hi> That holy Word of God which giveth Light and Underſtanding to the Simple, and is able to make us wiſe unto Salvation,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53101:19"/>and to ſave our Souls, if we believe the Bleſſed Author of it: That Word in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is kept from the People, leſt it ſhould make the Ways of God plain before their Faces, and ſhew them what a mighty Change in the Chriſtian Religion hath been made amongſt them. And that keeps the Vulgar in a State of Darkneſs and timorous Superſtition, and deprives them of thoſe Spiritual Joys and Improvements, which Divine Revelation would af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</p>
            <p>If any Book in the World can be truly pleaſant and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, it is the Holy Bible; wherein we ſee the infinite Wiſdom and Power and Providence of God, in the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Government of the World, and particularly in his Care for them that love and ſerve him: The ſacred Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is ſo full of Comfort in all Changes of Humane Life; the infinite Goodneſs and other Perfections of God are ſo clearly revealed in it, that by reading thereof, an attentive Chriſtian in all his Afflictions is inſpir'd with wiſe and good Thoughts, and Courage, and Firmneſs of Mind, and a joyful dependence upon God. Then the Mercies and My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of our Redemption, the Life and Death of our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, the Excellency of his Precepts, and of the Sermons and Writings of his Apoſtles, and the infinite Graciouſneſs of his Promiſes: Theſe are ſo raviſhing and ſo wonderful, ſo apt to ſupport our Spirits, and to nouriſh our Hopes, to give a good Man a fore-Taſte of the Joys of Heaven, and to bring us to the Likeneſs and the Senſe of God's Love, that nothing can give equal Comforts to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, or any ways ſupply the Want of theſe. It would be the greateſt Wonder why any Church that believes the Old and New Teſtament to be the Book of God, ſhould forbid the reading of it: but that the Contrariety betwixt their Traditions and thoſe Divine Writings is very appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to them that can conſult and compare both. That, or
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53101:20"/>nothing, muſt excuſe their Uncharitableneſs in taking the Divine Oracles from them, for whoſe Conſolation and Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance they were appointed.</p>
            <p>Again, they want the Comfort and Inſtruction of God's publick Worſhip. What Scriptures are read in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Aſſemblies of the Roman Communion, are in the Latin Tongue, by which the Underſtanding of the People is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred unfruitful. What Prayers and Supplications are put up to God, are in the ſame Language; they know not what is ſaid, and therefore cannot aſſent with their Hearts, nor excite ſuch devout Affections in their Souls as would recommend their common Requeſts to the Throne of Grace. Neither are the Celebrations of the Divine Goodneſs underſtood, they praiſe not God with joyful Lips: And that pious En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe they ſhould have with him, in paying their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and preſenting their Thanks and Petitions to his Divine Majeſty, being thus interrupted by their not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what is ſaid, they are deprived of one of the principal Means of Edification. 'Tis ſtrange it ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enter into the Hearts of Men, to offer to God for a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Service, Words of which they know not the Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification. And it renders ineffectual thoſe Acts of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which ſhould moſt affect and better the Hearts of Chriſtian Worſhippers, and raiſe up their Thoughts and their Affections to Heaven.</p>
            <p>From hence it is, that we have more knowledg of God, and more Underſtanding of the Chriſtian Religion. They amongſt us that really believe Chriſtianity, and would make ſure of the Happineſs it offers, by ſearching and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating of the Holy Scriptures, and by joyning with the publick Worſhip; whilſt they attend and underſtand what the Church ſaith to God, and what he ſaith to us, are much
<pb facs="tcp:53101:20"/>improved in thoſe great Principles of Religion which they learn'd in their Catechiſm, and are made to grow in Grace, and in the knowledg of the Lord. They have in theſe two, what perpetually informs their Judgment, and excites their Will to cleave to God and Goodneſs; and after their beſt Endeavours to rely upon thoſe infinite Mercies of God in Chriſt our Redeemer, on which the greateſt of Roman Champions confeſſed that it is moſt ſafe to repoſe our whole Truſt and Confidence.</p>
            <p>Anſwerable to thoſe, are the publick Exhortations of our Church, by the Mouth of her Miniſters, and the Books of Religious Inſtruction wherewith ſhe entertains her Children. Their Time and Zeal and Attention are not taken up in Sprinklings, Kiſſings of Reliques, going in Pilgrimage, viſiting of Shrines, paying devout Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to Saints and Images, and reciting Beads and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, and the Offices of St. <hi>Bridget,</hi> or the like. Neither theſe things, nor any of this Nature, which can neither inſtruct nor reform the World, nor give Comfort to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Souls, are recommended to our People: They are clearly taught wherein true Religion and ſubſtantial Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs conſiſt, and exhorted to lay on them the great Streſs of their Hopes and of their Endeavours, and devoutly to make uſe of thoſe means of Grace which are of Divine Appointment, and thereby to eſtabliſh their Hearts in the Love of God, and a chearful dependence upon the infinite Merits and Mercies of our dear Saviour.</p>
            <p>Nothing of the whole Counſel of God is by our Church kept back from us, our Belief is unqueſtionable, being tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Primitive and Univerſal; our Worſhip of God is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Will, and his moſt bleſſed Nature; and our Rule of Life and Converſation comprehends all Duties:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53101:21"/>To fear God, and honour the King, and love one another, and continue patient in well-doing. Ours is indeed a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine according to Godlineſs, and of it, it may be teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the Words of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter,</hi> that <hi>it is the true Grace of God, wherein we ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we are not wanting to our ſelves, we want nothing that can either ſhew us the Way to Happineſs, or help and forward us in it; we ought to expreſs our Charity to them that err, and want many of thoſe Bleſſings and Advantages which we have for the obtaining eternal Salvation; we ſhould earneſtly pray for them, and what we can promote their Inſtruction, but by no means fear their Threatnings and Sentences of Damnation.</p>
            <p>He that in earneſt would go to Heaven, and profeſſeth Chriſtianity, not to obtain Favour with Men, but to pleaſe God, and to ſave his immortal Soul, can be no where ſafer than in our Church. Therein he profeſſeth that Faith which all Chriſtian Communions hold to be truly Divine, and therein he may make his Calling and Election ſure, if he will but practiſe anſwerably to his Belief, add to his Faith Vertue, and not be unfruitful in the knowledg of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. The more he underſtands his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the more he will love it, and be convinc'd that he is in the right: And the more carefully he lives according to his Profeſſion, with a Conſcience void of Offence towards God and towards Men, the more aſſurance will he have that he ſhall be happy.</p>
            <p>All other Grounds of Hope beſides Truth and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs will prove vain. But he that ſtands upon the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the chief Corner-Stone: He that ſtudies and minds his Duty, and earneſtly begs for the Divine Aſſiſtance that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:53101:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>he may live to God, and remain faithful unto Death: he ſhall receive the Crown of Life, though ſome preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Men dare condemn him to Death.</p>
            <p>Whatever Confidence or high Pretences ſome may have, whatever Ways and Devices they invent for to gain Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: <hi>Chriſt is the Way, the Truth and the Life; no Man co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth unto the Father, but by him; there is no other Name un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heaven given unto Men, whereby they can be ſaved, but only the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; He that calleth and believeth on him ſhall not be confounded.</hi> Here let us fix, and not regard what Men ſay, nor what they can do: But look unto Jeſus the Author and Finiſher of our Faith, firmly relying on his Almighty Goodneſs, <hi>who is able to ſave them to the uttermoſt that come to God by him, being ever living to make Interceſſion for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:53101:22"/>
            <head>BOOKS lately Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Pillar and Ground of Truth. A Treatiſe ſhewing that the <hi>Roman Church</hi> falſly claims to be <hi>That Church,</hi> and the Pillar of <hi>That Truth</hi> mentioned by S. <hi>Paul</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy, Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 15. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>The Peoples Right to read the Holy Scripture Aſſerted. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>A Short Summary of the principal Controverſies between the Church of <hi>England</hi> and the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> being a Vindication of ſeveral Proteſtant Doctrines, in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to a Late Pamphlet, Intituled, <hi>[Proteſtancy deſtitute of Scripture Proofs.]</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>Two Diſcourſes; Of Purgatory, and Prayers for the Dead.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to a Late Pamphlet, Intituled, [The Judgment and Doctrine of the Clergy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> concerning one Special Branch of the King's Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, viz. <hi>In diſpenſing with the Penal Laws.]</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Notes</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> as laid down by Cardinal <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> examined and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preparation for Death:</hi> Being a Letter ſent to a young Gentlewoman in <hi>France,</hi> in a dangerous Diſtemper of which ſhe died.</p>
            <p>The Difference between the <hi>Church of England</hi> and the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to a late Book, Intituled, <hi>An Agreement between the Church of</hi> England <hi>and Church of</hi> Rome.</p>
            <p>A <hi>PRIVATE PRAYER</hi> to be uſed in Difficult Times.</p>
            <p>A True Account of a Conference held about Religion at <hi>London, Sept.</hi> 29, 1687, between <hi>A. Pulton,</hi> Jeſuit, and <hi>Tho. Tenniſon,</hi> D. D. as alſo of that which led to it, and followed after it. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>The Vindication of <hi>A. Creſſener,</hi> Schoolmaſter in <hi>Long-Acre,</hi> from the Aſperſions of <hi>A. Pulton,</hi> Jeſuit, Schoolmaſter in the <hi>Savoy,</hi> together with ſome Account of his Diſcourſe with Mr. <hi>Meredith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe ſhewing that Proteſtants are on the ſafer Side, notwithſtanding the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Judgment of their Adverſaries; and that <hi>Their Religion</hi> is the ſureſt Way to Heaven. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>Six Conferences concerning the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> wherein is ſhewed, that the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> overthrows the Proofs of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
